<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://ziheng-qi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://ziheng-qi.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-17T06:59:13+00:00</updated><id>https://ziheng-qi.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Thoughts on Suno AI v5.0 and the Future of Music Creation</title><link href="https://ziheng-qi.github.io/blog/2025/thoughts-on-suno-ai/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Thoughts on Suno AI v5.0 and the Future of Music Creation"/><published>2025-10-14T15:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-14T15:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://ziheng-qi.github.io/blog/2025/thoughts-on-suno-ai</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://ziheng-qi.github.io/blog/2025/thoughts-on-suno-ai/"><![CDATA[<p>I was shocked by the recently released Suno AI v5.0 model. As a guitar enthusiast and music lover, I was blown away by the quality of music this generation of AI can produce—truly studio-level output.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/suno_ai-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/suno_ai-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/suno_ai-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/suno_ai.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Suno AI v5.0: A new era in music generation </div> <p>Just a year ago, artists were loudly proclaiming that AI could never replace art or music. In just one year, those voices have gone quiet. It’s a humbling reminder of how rapidly technology evolves.</p> <h2 id="the-silver-lining">The Silver Lining</h2> <p>Looking at the bright side, AI has dramatically lowered the barrier to entry for creative work. It liberates people from the technical constraints, putting human expression at the center and preventing the “toolification” of creators. AI will likely disrupt commercial art, but it won’t kill art itself. In fact, AI development will benefit ordinary creators and music enthusiasts who previously lacked the resources or technical skills to bring their ideas to life.</p> <p>That said, for those hoping to make a living solely from songwriting, the current pace of development makes that path increasingly challenging.</p> <h2 id="a-historical-parallel">A Historical Parallel</h2> <p>When photography was invented centuries ago, painters felt similarly threatened. After all, no brushstroke, no matter how refined, could match the precision of a camera. But what did artists do? They pivoted toward the abstract, the expressive, and the purely artistic. They discovered creative paths that cameras couldn’t replicate—giving birth to Cubism, Impressionism, Fauvism, and Pop Art.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/picasso_painting-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/picasso_painting-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/picasso_painting-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/picasso_painting.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Picasso's abstract art: An artistic response to photography that explored new dimensions of expression </div> <p>I believe music will follow a similar trajectory. As AI makes pleasant, well-crafted music accessible to everyone, musicians will likely move toward purer, more experimental forms of expression. The democratization of music creation might push professional musicians to explore territories that AI cannot easily replicate—the deeply personal, the avant-garde, the emotionally raw.</p> <h2 id="final-thoughts">Final Thoughts</h2> <p>Rather than fearing AI, perhaps we should view it as a catalyst for artistic evolution. Just as photography didn’t kill painting but rather redefined it, AI music generation won’t kill music—it will reshape what it means to be a musician. The future might belong to those who can blend human creativity with AI capabilities, or those who dare to venture into artistic territories that machines cannot comprehend.</p> <p>As for me? I’ll continue strumming my guitar…</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="blog"/><category term="AI"/><category term="music"/><category term="creativity"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflections on AI-generated music and what it means for artists and music lovers]]></summary></entry></feed>